<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An abstract of the lives, precepts, and sayings, of the ancient fathers, which immediately succeeded Christ, and his apostles Faithfully collected, and published; as well for instruction and admonishion to all people: as for the encouragement of all such as suffer for the testimony of truth, and a good conscience. By a fellow sufferer with them, J.W.</title>
            <author>Whiting, John, 1656-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65929</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833731</idno>
  <idno type="VID">38209</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240939242</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222575</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833731</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833731e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65929)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38209)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2221:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An abstract of the lives, precepts, and sayings, of the ancient fathers, which immediately succeeded Christ, and his apostles Faithfully collected, and published; as well for instruction and admonishion to all people: as for the encouragement of all such as suffer for the testimony of truth, and a good conscience. By a fellow sufferer with them, J.W.</title>
                  <author>Whiting, John, 1656-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10, 13-17, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Howkins, in George-yard, in Lombard-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.W. = John Whiting.</note>
                  <note>Text appears continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisment leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Swarthmore College Library, Pennsylvania.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Fathers of the church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38209:1"/>
            <p>AN ABSTRACT OF THE Lives, Precepts, and Sayings, OF THE <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi> WHICH Immediately succeeded <hi>Christ,</hi> and his <hi>Apostles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully Collected, and Published; as well for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction and Admonishion to all people: as for the Encouragement of all such as Suffer for the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Truth, and a Good Conscience.</p>
            <p>By a Fellow Sufferer with them, <hi>J. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Howkins,</hi> in <hi>George-yard,</hi> in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-Street,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:38209:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38209:2"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT, OF THE Lives, Precepts, and Saying, of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. I <hi>Gnatius,</hi> (who saw Christ in the Flesh, and also, after his Resurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, being Twelve years old at his Crucifixion; and is supposed to be one of those Little Ones, which Christ took and set in the midst of them to teach his Disciples <hi>Humility.</hi>) He was Pastor of the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> next after the Apostle <hi>Peter,</hi> and Suffered Martyrdom for the <hi>Christian Faith,</hi> under <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperor; <hi>Anno Christ.</hi> III. being torn to pieces by Wild Beasts, at <hi>Rome;</hi> for Refusing, to <hi>Sacrifice to Idols:</hi> saying, after his Apprehension, <hi>Now do I begin to be a Disciple of Christ, I weigh or Regard, neither things Visible, or Invisible, so I may win Christ: Let Fire, Cross, breaking of my Bones, cuartering of my Members, crushing my Body, and all the Torments that Man, or the Devil can Invent, fall upon me, so I may Injoy my Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> &amp;c. His usual saying was, <hi>My Love is Crucified:</hi> meaning either Christ or his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the World; heused to say, <hi>That there is nothing better, than the Peace of a good Conscience. That Good, and Wicked men, are like true, and counterfeit Money; the one seems to be good, and is not, the other seems and is good. Other Graces are but parts of a Christians Armour, as the Shield
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38209:3"/>of Faith, the Sword of the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but Patience is the Panoply, or whole Armour of the Man of God; the Enemy foyls us without it, but, we foyl him by it. Grace flowing from the blessed Spirit of God, makes the Soul like a Fountain, whose Water is pure, wholsome and clear; for Grace beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, cleanseth, and so saveth the whole Man.</hi> He Writ many <hi>Epistles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> who was Disciple to St. <hi>John,</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Smyrna;</hi> being taken, and brought into the <hi>Theatre,</hi> the Pro-Consul urged him, to Blaspheme, and defie Christ; he said, Fourscore and six years have I ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Christ, neither hath he ever offended me in any thing, and how then can I Revile my Lord and King, that hath thus kept me; and when the Pro-Consul urged him to Swear, he refused, saying, I am a Christian: saying likewise, We are Commanded of God, to give unto Governors, and Powers, whom he hath Ordained, the Honour and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, which is due unto them, and not hurtful unto us. He was Burned at a Stake in <hi>Smyrna</hi> for the <hi>Faith of Christ;</hi> (as he fore saw in a Vision,) being Replenished from Above; insomuch, that the Fire refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to take hold of him: they ran him through with a Spear, so quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fire, and Sealing his Testimony with his Blood: (A faithful, and constant Witness to the Truth. <hi>Anno Christ.</hi> 170. He differed with <hi>Anicetus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> about the keeping of <hi>Easter,</hi> and other trivial things; by which they weakned one another: This I do not mention to Reflect upon either; believing, as one saith, There was much good in them both: but as a Caution to others, to beware of such things, and according to the Apostles Doctrine to <hi>Love one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Dionysius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> Born at <hi>Athens,</hi> where he was Convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he Preached there: as mentioned <hi>Acts</hi> the 17. Where he also Preached himself, and afterwards went into <hi>France</hi> to Preach the Gospel, where he was Apprehended at <hi>Paris,</hi> and after divers Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Beheaded; for <hi>Refusing to deny Christ:</hi> saying, Come Life, come Death I will Worship none but the God of Heaven, and Earth. He, used to say, That he desired these Two things of God; First, That he might know the <hi>Truth</hi> himself: And Secondly, That he might Preach it as he ought unto others. He suffered Martyrdom under <hi>Adrian: Anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sti</hi> 96.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> (so called of his Martyrdome;) Born at <hi>Neopolis</hi> in <hi>Palestine,</hi> at first a <hi>Philosopher,</hi> but being Converted, by the Chistians Sufferings, he became a Couragious Defender of the Truth against its op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers; for which he was much hated by the <hi>Heathen Philosophers,</hi> falsly so called, who procured his Death, as he fore-told; suffering Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for the <hi>Faith,</hi> being Beheaded under <hi>Verus,</hi> or <hi>Adrian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; <hi>Anno</hi> 189. (Saying, that Persecutors could kill, but could not hurt. He used to say, That which the Soul is in the Body, that are Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38209:3"/>in the World; for as the Soul is in, but not of the Body: so Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are in, but not of the World. Also, it is best of all, not to Sin; and next to that, to amend upon the Punishment. Again, that it is the greatest slavery in the World, to be subject to ones own Passions. He wrote Apologies for the Christians, taxing their Persecutors for Injustice, and Cruelty in Condemning them unheard, and without Cause; which moved <hi>Antoninus Pius</hi> to favor the Christians.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> (which signifies, <hi>A lover of Peace,</hi> his nature answering to his name:) Born in <hi>Asia,</hi> of <hi>Greek</hi> Parents, and afterwards Bishop of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where he suffered Martyrdom, with many others, for the <hi>Christian Profession,</hi> in the Fifth Persecution under <hi>Severus;</hi> being carryed between Two Hills, and put to their choice, to go either to a Cross on one hand and Dye, or to an Idol on the other and Live? but they chosing the Cross, was all put to Death, <hi>Anno</hi> 182. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> being Sixty, or as some say, Ninety Years of Age: He used to compare the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks</hi> of his time, to <hi>Esop's</hi> Dog, That lost the Substance of Religion whil'st they gaped too earnestly afterthe Shadow. Consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Vanity of all Earthly things, he said, What profit is there in that Honour which is so short lived, as that perchance it was not Yester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, neither will be to Morrow; and such men as labour so much for it, are but like Froth, which though it be uppermost, yet is unprofitablest. He sharply reproved <hi>Victor,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for Excommunicating all the <hi>Eastern</hi> Bishops for differing from him about the keeping of <hi>Easter,</hi> Miracles, and the Gift of Prophecying, continued in his time.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>African,</hi> Born at <hi>Carthage;</hi> a Man of great Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and well known in the Civil Law; after his Conversion, said, I now perceive, that we are not Born, but Made Christians. His usual Sayings were, If thou beest backward in thoughts of Repentance, be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the thoughts of Hell, the burning Flames whereof, onely the Tears of a Penitent Eye can Extinguish. If the Devils, without Christ's leave had no Power over the <hi>Gadarens</hi> Swine, much less have they Power over God's own Sheep. We should nottry Mens Faith, by their Persons; but their Persons, by their Faith. It's in vain to come to the God of Peace, without Peace; or to pray for the Remission of our own Sins, without forgiving others: we must not come ot make an Atonement with God, at his Altar, before we have made Atonement with our Brother in our Hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He wrote many excellent things, especially, his Apologie in Defence of the Christians; clearing them of the Accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons laid to their Charge: and shewing, the more they were cut down, the more they encreased; the Blood of the Christians proving the Seed of the <hi>Church:</hi> which disswaded the Emperor <hi>Severus</hi> from Persecuting them. It is Reported, that at last through emulation, or strife between
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38209:4"/>him, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy: he fell into the Error of <hi>Montanus;</hi> but it is not probable: however, Let him that standeth, take heed lest he fall. He flourished under <hi>Severus,</hi> and dyed in Peace; <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 202. Aged 63.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> Flourished about the Year of Christ, 196. Though his Country, Parentage and Education is uncertain, some think, he was Born at <hi>Athens,</hi> and lived at <hi>Alexandria</hi> whence he was so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: He used to say, That such as adorn themselves with Gold, and think themselves bettered thereby, are worse than Gold, and not Lords of it; as all that have it, ought to be: out of the depth, and bowels of the Earth, hath God discovered, and shewed Gold unto men; and they have made it the occasion of all Mischief and Wickedness: Gold to many men is much dearer, than their Faith and Honesty, and the love of it makes many so Covetous, as if they were to live here for ever: Avarice is not the Vice of Gold, but of Men which use it wickedly. He complained, of the want of Zeal, and Power of Godliness in his time. The time, and manner of his Death is also uncertain.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. <hi>Origen</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Born of Christian Parents, <hi>Anno</hi> 189. and Scholar to <hi>Clements:</hi> A Man famous for Piety and Learning, even from his Childhood; the first that Writ Commentaries on the Scriptures, and taking them too Literally Erred in many thing He used to say, That God's Providence hath Ordained all things, for some end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: he made not Malice, and though he can Restrain it, yet he will not; for if Malice were not, Vertue should not have a contrary, and so could not shine so Clear; for the Malice of <hi>Josephs</hi> Brethren, was the means whereby God brought about many admirable Works of his Providence, as the story sheweth: He suffered great, and grievous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions, and Afflictions for <hi>Christ's sake,</hi> in the Raign of <hi>Decius, viz.</hi> Bands and Torments in his Body; Rackings, with Bars of Iron; Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, with terrible threats of Death, and Burning; and divers other Torments; all which he manfully endured for the <hi>Gospel sake:</hi> He had a desire of Martyrdom from his Infancy, and would have Suffered with his Father at Seventeen Years old, had he not been Restrained; he used much to encourage such as was to Suffer; whereby he often brought himself into danger, sometimes hardly escaping: at length, going to encourage and strengthen some that was carried to an <hi>Idol Temple</hi> to Sacrifice, they caught hold of him, and induced him to Sacrifice; so that through seat, he consented, and so fell from the Faith, of which, he afterwards made Great: and doleful Lamentation, and through deep Contrition, was again Restored; and at last, dyed in Peace: under <hi>Gallus</hi> and <hi>Volusian, Anno</hi> 220. Aged 69. It is said of him, That as he Taught, so he Lived; and as he Lived so he Taught.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38209:4"/> IX. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> an <hi>African</hi> born at <hi>Carthage,</hi> and afterwards Bishop thereof, wherein he behaved himself as a good Example of Humility to others; and foresaw in a Vision the approaching Persecution of the Christians, and that their unfaithfulness was the fore-runner thereof, which soon after followed. In which Persecution he was apprehended, and Sentenced to be Beheaded for refusing to Sacrifice, which he chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully yielded to, suffering Martyrdom for the Faith of Christ under <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerian</hi> and <hi>Gallien, Anno</hi> 259. He had many excellent Sayings, whereof these are some, Let not that sleep in thy Treasury that may be profitable to the Poor; he that gives an Alms to the Poor, offers a sweet smelling sacrifice to God. That which a man must necessarily sometime part with, it's wisdom for him to distribute it, so that God may everlasting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reward him. Women that pride themselves in putting on Silk and Purple, cannot lightly put on the Lord Jesus Christ. They which colour their Locks with Yellow and Red, begin betimes to prognosticate of what colour their hair shall be in Hell; they which love to paint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in this world otherwise than God Created them, may justly fear that at the Resurrection their Creator will not know them.—All injury of evils present is to be neglected for the hope of good things to come. To set out vertue in words, and by Deeds to destroy the same, is nothing worth.—And in another Book he mentions twelve absurdities in the life of Man, <hi>viz.</hi> A wise man without good Works, An old man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Religion, A young man without obedience, A rich man without Alms, A woman without shamefaceness, A Guide without vertue, A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious Christian, A poor man that is proud, A King that is unjust, A Bishop that is negligent, People without Discipline, and Subjects with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law. He was much addicted to Reading, especially <hi>Tertullian,</hi> saying, when he called for him, Give me my Master.</p>
            <p n="10">X. <hi>Arnobius</hi> of <hi>Sicca</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> used to say, that Persecution brings Death in one hand and Life in the other, for while it kills the body, it crowns the Soul; He flourished under <hi>Dioclesian</hi> between the year 300 and 330.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. <hi>Eusebius</hi> Bishop of <hi>Caesarea</hi> in <hi>Pallestina,</hi> who was very studious in the holy Scriptures, and with <hi>Pamphilus</hi> a diligent searcher of the Divine Library, he refused to leave the little Bishoprick of <hi>Caesarea</hi> for the great one of <hi>Antioch,</hi> for which <hi>Constantine</hi> the Emperour commended him, and used to say that he was worthy to be Bishop not of one City only but of the whole World, for his familiarity with <hi>Pamphilus</hi> the Martyr; he was called <hi>Eusebius Pamphilus</hi> he used to say, that <hi>Moses</hi> wrote the old Law in dead Tables of Stone, but Christ did write the perfect docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the New Testament in Living Souls. He wrote the Ecclesia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stical History of the first Three Hundred years from Christ to <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38209:5"/>and divers other Books. He was Reputed an <hi>Arian</hi> by some, but it was not really so, for he profest (saith <hi>Scultetus</hi>) the Eternity of Christ, though his Co-equality with the Father he did not absolutely believe; He flourished under <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great, and died 340.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. <hi>Lactantius</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> by birth, and Schollar to <hi>Arnobius,</hi> used to say, That Godliness alwaies enriches the possessor; he flourished under <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> (being preserved in the Persecutions) <hi>Anno</hi> 300.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. <hi>Athanasius</hi> born at <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and after <hi>Alexander</hi> Bishop thereof, but being much envied for his uprightness; he suffered great persecutions and reproaches by the <hi>Arians,</hi> under <hi>Constantius.</hi> In the midst of his troubles he used to say, Though an Army should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp about me, yet would I not fear. After many banishments and sufferings many waies, being preserved in many dangers, he at last (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all their envy) returned, and died in peace in his own City, <hi>Anno Chr.</hi> 375. It's said he stood firm against all the world.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. <hi>Hilary</hi> Bishop of <hi>Poictiers</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> nobly descended and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Gifts, flourished <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 355. and died in peace under <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian</hi> and <hi>Valence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">XV. <hi>Cyrill</hi> Bishop of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> at first an <hi>Arian,</hi> but after his Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation constant in the Faith, used to say, Some come to the Church to see Fashions, others to meet their Friends, yet it's better to come so than not at all: In the mean time the Net is cast out, and they which intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing less are drawn into Christ, who catches them not to destroy them, but that being dead he may bring them to Life Eternal; he died <hi>Anno Chr.</hi> 365.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. <hi>Ephremsyrus</hi> born in <hi>Nisilea,</hi> of a Holy life and Charitable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposion, used to say that the resolute traveller knows that his Journey is long and the way dirty; yet goes on in hope to come to his House. So let a Christian (though the way to Heaven be narrow, though it be set with Troubles and Persecutions) yet let him go on till he hath fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished his Course with joy, for Heaven is his home: And again, he that feasts his Body, and starves his Soul, is like him that feasts his Slave, and starves his Wife. He died under <hi>Valens. Anno Chr.</hi> 404.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. <hi>Basil</hi> (called the <hi>Great,</hi> from his great parts) born in <hi>Pontus,</hi> afterwards Bishop of <hi>Cesarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> of a strict and holy life, as many of the Fathers was, used to say, To know thy self is very difficult, for as the eye can see all things but it self, so some can dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all Faults but their own.— And again, Divine Love is a never-fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treasure, he that hath it is Rich, and he that wanteth it is poor. He was Couragious and Constant in all his Sufferings, under <hi>Valens</hi> the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emperour, using excellent Speeches to his Persecutors. He flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished about the year, 370. and dyed in peace.</p>
            <p n="18">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:38209:5"/> XVIII. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> (so called from the place in <hi>Cappadocia</hi> where he was Bishop) sometime contemporary with <hi>Basil,</hi> used to say, That in a great multitude of people of several Ages and Conditions, who are like a Harp with many strings, it is hard to give every one such a touch in Preaching, as may please all, and offend none. It's said, That what his Doctrine was, such was his Life. He loved Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and had a desire of Martyrdom, yet died in peace, for what we find. He flourished under <hi>Theodosius, Anno Chr.</hi> 370.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> born in <hi>Palestine,</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Salamine</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> who flourished, <hi>Anno</hi> 370. much esteemed for Piety and Holyness of Lise: of whom it is said, That his Doctrine approved his Life, and his Life defended his Doctrine. He used to say, That he never let his adversary sleep, (not that he disturbed him in his sleep, but) because he agreed with him presently, and would not let the <hi>Sun go down upon his wrath:</hi> Yet there was great Difference between him and <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> about the Books of <hi>Origen,</hi> which did them much hurt. The more is the pity, that such eminent men should bend their strength, in contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one with another. When in his return from <hi>Constantinople</hi> he was sick, nigh unto Death, he called his Friends, and said to them, God bless you, my Children, for <hi>Epiphanius</hi> shall fee your faces no more in this life, and so dyed on the Sea, much lamented, aged 115. years.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. <hi>Ambrose,</hi> a Prefects son in <hi>France,</hi> first Lieutenant, and then made Bishop of <hi>Millain,</hi> where he ruled with great Authority (too much like a Lordly Bishop) excommunicating <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Emperour, and keeping him out till he submitted. He used to say, When Gold is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered thee, thou usest not to say, I will come again to morrow and take it, but art glad of the present possession; but Salvation being offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our Souls, few men haste to embrace it: And again, It is not so much to be enquired, how much thou givest, as with what heart. It's not Liberality, when thou tak'st by Oppression from one, and giv'st to another. And again, A clear Conscience should not regard slanderous Speeches, nor think that they have more power to condemn him, than his own Conscience hath to clear him. And again, Death is the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of all Vices, for it is the Progress and Accomplishment of the full Mortification of all our Earthly Members, wherein that filthy flux of fin is dryed up in an instant: it is a voluntary sacrificing of the whole Man, Soul and Body to the Lord, the greatest and highest Service we can do him upon Earth. He dyed <hi>Anno Chr.</hi> 397.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. <hi>Gregory</hi> sirnamed <hi>Nissen,</hi> from the City where he was Bishop in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> where he was born, and said to be Brother to <hi>Basil;</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Cesarea</hi> aforesaid, though it agrees not with the time they lived in. He compared the Usurer to a man giving water to one in a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38209:6"/>Feavor, which doth him no good, but a great deal of mischief; so the Usurer, though he seem for the present to relieve his Brothers want, yet afterwards he doth greatly torment him. He gave this Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of an Usurer, He loves no Labour but a sedentary Life, the Pen is his Plough, Parchment his Field, Ink his seed, time is the Rain to ripen his greedy Desires, his Sickle is calling in of Forfeitures, his House the Barn where he winnows the Fortunes of his Clients: He follows his Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors as Eagles and Vultures do Armies, to prey upon the dead Corps. And again, Men come to Usurers as Birds to an heap of Corn, they desire the Corn, but are destroyed in the Nets. And again, There is no excuse for Hardheartedness, for where can a rich man cast his Eyes, but he may behold Objects of his Charity? He flourished, <hi>Anno Chr.</hi> 480. and dyed under <hi>Valentinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">XXII. <hi>Theodoret</hi> (which signifies <hi>the Gift of God</hi>) was born at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> (who wrote, in like manner as <hi>Socrates</hi> did, the Ecclesiastical History after <hi>Eusebius</hi>) he used to say, That the Delights of the Soul are, To know her Maker, to consider his Works, and to know her own Estate. He flourished, <hi>Anno Chr.</hi> 420. and dyed under <hi>Theodosius junior.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. <hi>Hierom</hi> (commonly called St. <hi>Jerome</hi>) born at <hi>Seridon</hi> in the Confines of <hi>Dalmatia</hi> and <hi>Panonia, Anno Chr.</hi> 331. of godly Parents, who educated him after the best manner, as he grew in years he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled into divers Countries, getting acquaintance with the Chiefest men then in being, and went through many Difficulties and Troubles from the adverse party, for the Truths sake. He used this excellent Saying, If my Father stood weeping on his knees before me, and my Mother hanging on my neck behind me, and all my Brethren and Sisters, Children and Kinsfolks, howling on every side, to retain me in a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Life, I would fling my Mother to the ground, run over my Father, despise all my Kindred, and tread them under my feet, that I might run to Christ.—He used to say, Dead flesh is to be cut off for fear of a Gangren.—And again, You must be a Dove, and a Serpent; one not to do hurt to others, the other not to be hurt by others. And again, That woman is truly Chaste, that hath Liberty and Opportunity to sin, and will not. And again, All Vertues are so linked together, that he that hath one hath all, and he that wants one wants all. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he did, he still thought that Voice was in his ears, <hi>Arise ye dead, and come to judgment.</hi> His usual Prayer was, Lord, let me know my self, that I may the better know thee the Saviour of the World. He translated the Bible out of the Originals into Latine, which goes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his name to this day. He dyed under <hi>Honorius, Anno Christi</hi> 422. Aged 91.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:38209:6"/> 24. <hi>John Chrysostom,</hi> so called of his Golden-stile, born at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> of the race of the Senators, Disciple to <hi>Libaneus</hi> or <hi>Eusebius</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> a bold and resolute man, &amp; of free speech, who feared not to tell any their faults to their faces be it King or Queen, whereupon the Empress was so offended with him that she procured his banishment: As he went out of the City he said, none of these things trouble me. <hi>The Earth is the Lords and the fulness thereof,</hi> &amp;c. He used to say, as a great shower of rain extinguisheth the force of fire, so meditation on Gods Word puts out the fire of Lust in the Soul, and as a Boat over-laden sinks, so, much Wealth drowns men in perdition, and, A bulwark of Adamant is not more impregnable, than the Love of Bretheren, and, as a Rock though Winds and Waves beat against it, is immoveable, so, Faith grounded on the Rock Christ holds out in all temptations and Spiritual Combats. And the Devils first assault is vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, resist that, and his second will be weaker, and that being resisted, he proves a Coward. He flourished <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 400. And died in exile according to <hi>Epiphanius</hi>'s desire, as hedyed on the Sea according to <hi>Chrysostom</hi>'s desire, so having their wishes one of another, for at their last parting, <hi>Epiphanus</hi> told <hi>John Crysostom,</hi> that he hoped he would never die a Bishop, and <hi>John</hi> told him again that he hoped he would never come a live into his own Contrey, both which came to pass as is beforesaid. I only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it as a caution to all to be ware of such wishes one by another, least God suffer it to take effect: He was of an Austere Life, contemning Riches, and was much beloved in his place. It's said of him that he never told a lye, cursed any, or spoke any scurrillous matter.</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Augustine,</hi> by Birth an <hi>African</hi> Born at <hi>Thagasta</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa.</hi> In his youthful daies of vitious manners, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous judgment, but after his Conversion of a Godly, Chast and Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Life, of whom its written that after his Conversion having Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stized himself much by Fasting, Watching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To overcome his inward corruptions, and finding it ineffectual, as he was meditating what to do, he heard a voice saying <hi>In te stas &amp; non stas,</hi> which he rightly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting found that what he had strove to do in his own will and strength was only the work of Gods Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> lamenting himself in his confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions to Godsaying, I sought theewithout and thou wast within, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He used to say, that holy marriage is better than proud Virginity, and again, prayer that is pure and holy, pierceth Heaven, and returns not empty, it's a shelter to the Soul, a sacrifice to God, and a scourge to the Devil, and again, there is nothing that more abateth sin then the frequent medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of death. He cannot dye ill that liveth well, and seldom doth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38209:7"/>he dye well that lived ill, A Christian at home in his house must think himself a stranger, And again, if men want wealth, it is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly Gotten. If they have it, they ought by Good Works to lay it up in Heaven, He that hath tasted of the sweetness of divine Love, will not care for temporal sweetness. The Reasonable soul made in the likeness of God, may find much careful distraction, but no full satisfaction, for it being capable of God can be satisfyed with nothing but God, not to be without affliction but to overcome affliction is blessedness, Love is strong as death, for as death hills the body, so love of Eternal life kills Worldy desires and affections, He called ingratitude the Devils sponge, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he wipes out all the favours of the Almighty, He Praised one who when he was sick said, I have not lived so, that I am ashamed to live longer, nor do I fear to dye, having so good a Master to go to, His usual wish was, that Christ when he came might find him either praying or preaching, His prayer was, Lord give first what thou requirest, and then require of me what thou wilt, And, he that prayes well cannot chose but live well, when some upbraided him with the impieties of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life, look (said he) how much they blame my former faults, by so much the more I commend my Physician. He would not admit any Woman to live in his house, to prevent suspicion and scandal nor speak with any alone to avoid temtptation, He lived mean in apparrel, furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and dyet, and dyed in peace not long after the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> broke outof <hi>Spain</hi> and made such havock in <hi>Africa,</hi> (Especially <hi>Manritania</hi> burning of Citys, depopulating Towns and Villages, deflouring Virgins, and filling all places with Rapine and Spoile.) A little before they took <hi>Hippo,</hi> according to his desire, in the third Month of the seige, <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 430. Aged 76. He made no Will, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to bestow but Books, He wrote many Books of great esteem, especially that, of the City of God, and his Confessions, which have greatly delighted me, having many serious and sensible things in it, He seems to me to be the chiefest of the Fathers, and was certainly a man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous many waies in his day, and I beleive knew the power of God to salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet he held some errors, as <hi>Origen,</hi> and some others also did, which ought to be attributed to that night of darkness that was coming over all, and began in their daies to eclipse the Glory of the Christian Churches, He was called the hammer against hereticks.</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Cyril</hi> Bishop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> by Birth a <hi>Grecian</hi> who flourished <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 430. He used to say, it's the best way for a Rich man to make the bellies of the poor his barn, to succour the Fatherless and needy and thereby to lay up treasure in Heaven, that he may be received into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38209:7"/>Everlasting Habitations. And, where the Scriptures wants a tongue of expression, we need not lend an ear of attention, we may safely knock at the Council door of Gods Secrets, but if we go further we may be more bold than welcom: And again, the Devil Runs with open mouth upons Gods Children to devour them, they manfully Resist him, he thinks to weaken their Faith, and they by his Assaults are made the stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he Fights against them but they get ground upon him and so what he intended for their Destruction, full sore against his Will, makes for their Advantage, he dyed <hi>Anno Christi,</hi> 448.</p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Petrus Chrysologus</hi> (so called of his great Eloquence) born at <hi>Imo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> used to say, Let not thy Care be to have thy hands full whilst the Poors are empty, for the only way to have full Barns is to have Charitable Hands, And, God had rather men should love him than fear him, to be called father then master, he wins by merey that he may not punish by justice, if thou wilt be like thy Father, do likewise: And neither in the Flint alone, nor in the Steel alone, any fire is to be seen, nor extracted but by conjunction and collusion, so nor by Faith alone, nor by Good Works alone, is Salvation attained, but by joyning them both together, And as the Clouds darken Heaven, so intemperate banqueting the mind, as the violence of Winds and Waves sinks a ship, so drunkeness and gluttony our Souls and Bodies in the depth of Hell, and vertues separated are anihillated, Equity without Goodness is Severity, and Justice without Piety, is cruelty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He lived long, and dyed <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 500.</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Prosper,</hi> Born in <hi>Aquitane</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Rhegium</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> Schollar to <hi>Augustine,</hi> famous for Piety and Learning, he used to say, thou shalt neither hate the man for his vice nor love the vice for the mans sake, And thou boasts of thy Wealth, Honour, Strength, Beauty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider what thou art by sin, and shalt be in the grave, And they plumes will fall for every proud man forgets himself. And as the Soul is the life of the Body, so the life of the Soul is God, when the Soul departs the Body dyes, and when God departs the Soul dyes, And those things which God would have searched into are not to be neglected, but those which God would have hidden, are not to be searched into, by the Latter we become unlawfully curious, and by the neglect of the Former damnably ingrateful, And the envious man hath so many tortures, as the envied hath praisers, it's the Justice of envy to kill and torment the envious, And the Life to come is blessed Eternity, and Eternal blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, there is certain security, secure Quietness, Quiet Joyfulness, Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Eternity, Eternal felicity. He dyed in peace, <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 466.</p>
            <p n="29">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:38209:8"/> 29. <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> desended of the race of the Senators of the ancient City of <hi>Carthage,</hi> who in his youth forsook the Glory of the World to lead a private Life, and afterwards chosen Bishop of <hi>Ruspa</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> he used to say, Christ dyed for Men and Angels, for Men that they might rise from sin, and for Angels that they might not fall into sin. If they go to hell that do not Feed the hungry, Cloath the naked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> what will become of them that take away Bread from the hungry, Cloaths from the naked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If want of Charity be tormented in hell, what will become of the covetous, he suffered much by the <hi>Arians,</hi> even beatings and banishments, and in the midst of his greatest sufferings he used to say, we must suffer more than this for Christ, he dyed in peace (though in troublesome times) <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 529. Aged 65.</p>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Gregory</hi> the great Born at <hi>Rome</hi> of noble parentage (his Father being a Senator yet most noble for their piety) by some accounted the first Pope, or else the last Bishop thereof he lightly esteemed of his Greatness, saying, that all Earthly Glory was miserable, if the owner of it did seek after the Glory of God, and was very strict in spending his time, saying he was to give account of it to God. On a time seeing some <hi>English</hi> Boys in the Market at <hi>Rome</hi> to be sold he took such a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them that he would have come into <hi>Britian</hi> himself to convert the <hi>English Saxons,</hi> but being prevented he afterwards (when he was Bishop sent <hi>Austin</hi> the Monk into <hi>England</hi> to preach the Gospel (such as it was) there, He used to say, he is poor whose soul is void of Grace, not whose Coffers are empty of mony, <hi>Contented Poverty is true Riches,</hi> and again God is never absent, though the Wicked have him not in their thoughts, where he is not by favour, he is by punishment and terror, He could never read these Words <hi>Son Remember in thy life time thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedst good things,</hi> without horrour and astonishment, least having such Honours and dignities as he had, he should be excluded from his portion in Heaven, It is said of him that he was the worst <hi>Roman</hi> Bishop of all that were before him, and the best of all that followed him (still growing worse and worse) He severely reprehended the Bishop of <hi>Constantinople</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siring to be called Universal, Calling it that name of blasphemy, and yet soon after excepted of it themselves, for <hi>Phocas</hi> killing his Master <hi>Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> to be Emperor, to gratify the Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> gave him the title of Pope or Universal Bishop over all others. He lived under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Mauritius</hi> and dyed the second year of <hi>Phocas, Anno Ch.</hi> 605.</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Isidoris,</hi> by Birth a <hi>Spaniard</hi> and Bishop of <hi>Sevill,</hi> of great fame for his Life and Learning, He used to say knowledg and a good life are both profitable, yet if both cannot be obtained, a good life is to be sought
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38209:8"/>rather than much knowledg, and, as the Viper is killed by the young ones in her belly, so are we betrayed and killed by our own thoughts, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished in our bosoms, which consume and poyson the Soul, all things may be shun'd, but a mans own heart, a man cannot run from himself, a guilty Conscience will not forsake him, wheresoever he goes, and he that begins to grow better, let him beware least he grow proud, least vain glory give him a greater overthrow then his former vices. He dyed in the reign of <hi>Heraclius</hi> the Emperor, about the year 675.</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Bedae,</hi> (called venerable) an <hi>English Saxon</hi> born near the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastry called <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> in <hi>Wyramundas</hi> where he was brought up, he used to say, he is a sluggard that would reign with God, and not La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for God, in the promised reward he takes delight, but the Comanded Combats do afright him, And, anger doth Languish, by suppressing, but flames higher by expressing, He was Studious and Religious, and it's said a terrour to such as was proud and wicked. He dyed about 735. Aged, 70.</p>
            <p n="33">33. <hi>John Damascen</hi> born at <hi>Damascus</hi> a Learned man flourished under <hi>Leo, Anno Ch.</hi> 730. And dyed in peace.</p>
            <p n="34">34. <hi>Theophilact</hi> Born in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and afterwards Bishop of the same, used to say, be not troubled if this man lives in tranquility, and thou in tribulation, God will have it so, he puts thee into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, thou must therefore sweat hard before thou comest off with Victory, whereas he that comes forward in the World, goes back in Grace, his Estate is miserable that goes laughing to destruction, as a fool to the stocks for correction, he flourished <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 880.</p>
            <p n="35">35. <hi>Anselm</hi> born at <hi>Aosta</hi> or <hi>Angusta,</hi> at the foot of the <hi>Alps</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi> afterwards Arch-Bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> about the time of <hi>William Rufus</hi> between whom there was much difference (like as was between <hi>Becket</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Second for adhering to the Pope more then to him) he used to say, that if he should see the shame of sin on the one hand, and the pains of Hell on the other, and must of necessity choose one, he would rather be thrust into hell without sin, than go into Heaven with sin, and again, O hard hap what did man lose? What did he find? He lost the blessedness to which he was made to, and found death to which he was not made. He flourished <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1080.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> who flourished <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1110. Said God beholds and moderates all our actions, using the scourge of affliction for our casti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and conversion, and after due correction, shews his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affection, to those that trust in him for Salvation, and Christ asked <hi>Peter</hi> three times if he loved him, not for his own information, but that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38209:9"/>by his threefold profession he might help and heal his threefold negation, It is said he was a great light when the World was in great darkness by his Life and doctrine illuminating many.</p>
            <p n="37">37. <hi>Bernard</hi> Born at <hi>Fountane</hi> in <hi>Burgandie</hi> who contemned Worldly things for Christ sake, shuned company, and affected retirement giving himself to meditations and lived very strictly for the Love of vertue moderating his youthly affections by abstinence and rigour to nature in which he was exemplary, perswading some of his brothers to leave the World and go live with him in a monastery (which in those days was rather used for Religion sake than an idle life) as they was going they saw their Younger Brother at play, to whom the Elder said farewell Brother, we leave you all our Earthly possessions, to whom he answered, you take Heaven and leave me the Earth, this is not Equal, and so joyned with them in that course of life, living after a very strict and Religious manner, he used to say ambition is a guilded misery a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret poyson, a hidden plague, the Ingeneer of deceit, Mother of hipocrisie, the parent of envy, the original of vices, the moth of holiness, the blinder of hearts, turning medicines into maladies, and remedies into diseases when ever he came to the Church door (so called) He used to say to himself stay here all my Worldly thoughts &amp; all vanity that I may entertain Heavenly meditations, he was a good and pious man in many things, yet he was blamed for being too jealous and credulous of false reports, whereby he many times opposed better men than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, he differed from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in many things, Complaining that Popes and Bishops were the greatest persecutors of Christ, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He dyed <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1153. Aged 63.</p>
            <p n="38">38. <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> born at <hi>Navaria,</hi> and afterwards Bishop of <hi>Paris,</hi> used to say, there can no good dwell in us, that cannot will good, nor can wee perfect good, that cannot desire good, there are in us evil concupicenses and desires, which are the devils weapons, whereby when God forsakes us, he overthrows us, and gives our Souls a deadly wound. God condemns none before he sins, nor Crowns any before he overcomes, Let none glory in the Gifts of preachers, in that they edifie more by them, for they are not Authors of Grace, but Ministers, the instruction of words is not so powerful as the exhortation (or example) of works, for if they that teach well neglect to live well, they shall hardly profit their audience, he was contemporary with <hi>Gratian</hi> and dyed, <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1164.</p>
            <p n="39">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38209:9"/> 39. <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hales</hi> in <hi>Gloucestershire</hi> (reputed the founder of the Un<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versities) travelling into other connteries read divinity at <hi>Paris,</hi> his sayings were, a soul patient when wrongs are offered, is like a man with a sword in one hand and Salve in the other, Could wound but will heal. What the eye is to the body, faith is to the Soul, it's good for direction if it be kept well, and as flyes hurts the eye, so little sins and ill thoughts the Soul. Covetousness deserves the hatred of all for six reasons. 1. It's a sin against nature making the Soul terrene, which should be Caelestial. 2. For the many curses against it, wo to them that joyn house to house, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. For the many evils it subjects us to, it's the root of all evil. 4. It makes a man a fool, <hi>O fool this night,</hi> &amp;c. 5. It causes strifes, from whence are strifes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 6. It brings men into snares which drown in perdition. Every lye is odious, but that most which is against points of faith; as to say Christ was not born of the Virgin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Faith must be defended not opposed; an humble man is like a good tree the more full of fruits the branches are the lower they bend themselves. He dyed <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1245.</p>
            <p n="40">40. <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> Born near <hi>Naples</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> who with <hi>Bonaventure</hi> (as good a man, tho' perhaps not so Learned as himself) was Schollar to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hales,</hi> and taught the Sciences at <hi>Paris, Rome,</hi> &amp;c. It's said he was alwaies at his book, disputations or meditations, and was called Doctor <hi>Angelicus,</hi> he used to say that a day will come when fair dealing shall be found a Jewel, when a good Conscience shall be better than a good purse, for then the Judge will not be put off with fair words, nor drawn aside with hope of reward. And make much of time, especially in that weighty matter of Salvation, O how much would he that now lies frying in hell, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce if he might have but the least moment of time wherein he might get Gods favour! and the young man hath death at his back, the old man before his eyes, and that's the more dangerous Enemy, that persues thee then that which marches up toward thy face. Remember that tho' God promise forgiveness to repentant sinners, yet he hath not promised that they shall have to morrow to repent in. He died as he was going to the Council at Lyons, <hi>Anno Ch.</hi> 1274.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ends the</hi> Fathers <hi>and their</hi> Sayings, <hi>I have a Second sheet or two of the Chiefest of the first Reformers, and Protestant Martyrs, to be published hereafter if this find acceptance.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:38209:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38209:10"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed and Sold by Thomas Howkins.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>FIsher</hi>'s Works, <hi>Folio,</hi> Price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Howgill</hi>'s Works, <hi>Fol.</hi> 10 <hi>s</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pennington</hi>'s Works, <hi>Fol.</hi> 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Firebrands quenched, <hi>Quarto,</hi> 3 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Everard</hi>'s Works, <hi>Octavo,</hi> 6 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>No Cross, no Crown,</hi> by <hi>William Pen,</hi> 8vo, 2 <hi>s,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Divine Immediate Revelations,</hi> in 4to, 1 <hi>s.</hi> 2 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Keith</hi>'s Way cast up, 8vo, 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Truths Defence, 8vo, 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—His Rector Corrected, 8vo, 1 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Accusers Brethren, 8vo. 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Narrow Path of Divine Truth, or the Sayings of <hi>Matthew Weyer,</hi> 120, 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cabalistical Dialogues, in Answer to the Opinion of a Learned Doctor in Phylosophy and Theology, That the World was made of Nothing, 4to, 4<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>George Fox</hi>'s Tythes, Offerings, and First-fruits, 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Cause why <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were driven out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise, and the <hi>Jews</hi> out of their own Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:38209:11"/>
               <item> —Trying of Spirits in our Ages now, as in the Apostles Days, by the Spirit of Christ anointing within 4to, 2 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>—Word of Admonition, to all such as wander, 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi> ½.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Ellwood</hi>'s Caution to Constables, 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi> ½.</item>
               <item>— A Seasonable Disswasive from Persecution, 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— A Discourse concerning Riots, 4to, 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mather</hi>'s Manual: the second Edition, with large Additions, 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>, 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Heywood</hi>'s Friendly Persuasion and Christian Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all who profess the Guidance of the Spirit of Christ and Christianity, a large Broad-side, 1 <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>William Stoveg</hi>'s Epistle to Friends, being an Exhortation to Friends to continue Faithful in their Testimony in this Trying Time, a Broad side, ½.</item>
               <item>Artless Midnight Thoughts of a Gentleman at Court, 12<seg rend="sup">o</seg>, 2 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>School-Books of all sorts, Bibles of all sorts, Stationary Ware, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Paper, Paper-Books, Journals and Ledgers, Wax, Wafers, Ink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horns, Blank Bonds of various sorts.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>